[Music]
thank you hello and welcome to holotalk
the internet radio broadcast for lasers
and holography enjoyed by listeners
throughout the world I'm Frank defreitis
and I'll be your host for each
installment bringing you news guests and
everything holographic now please enjoy
the latest show
[Music]
hello Frank de Freitas
calling from the UK how are you uh fine
very well thank you and you pretty good
thank you for calling not at all it is
the right time isn't it oh it's it's the
perfect time welcome to holotalk thanks
very much I uh I just did one of the
Apollo Astronauts yesterday that's
amazing wow what's his name his name is
Dr Edgar Mitchell he was the captain
that took the module down onto uh onto
the moon's surface all right yeah that
is incredible so you're in good company
I'm absolutely amazing wow because NASA
were I mean NASA were involved in
holography at one one point weren't they
oh yeah very much so but Dr Mitchell is
more involved with the holographic
theory of the universe and how it
applies to extra sensory perception and
uh thought human thought right okay yeah
very very similar to uh pibrum's uh uh
theory of the holographic brain and
things of that nature fantastic yeah
well it's good to have you on the show
excellent thank you very much you're a
fellow pseudocolor holographer rice okay
yeah that's it yeah I mean have you have
you um have you been involved in that
kind of stuff before as well it's it's
my favorite type of hologram to do
although I must admit I don't remember
seeing many pseudo-color Holograms where
someone color mixes the way that you do
usually the individual exposures and the
individual colors are independent of one
another within the hologram
you actually do the color mixing where
if it's a bronze type of Statue the
statue turns out bronze from using
pseudocolor technique absolutely I mean
you know it's it's it's a bit more
challenging I suppose trying to trying
to achieve you know very specific colors
what got you started and what made you
choose doing pseudocolor and also
explain to the listeners exactly what
sudo color is
Cedar color really is is creating colors
in a sense artificially
um so you're using
um chemistry you're using um in this in
in my case a chemical called
triathanolamine I think probably in most
other people's cases as well and
so by by swelling the uh silver halide
Emulsion to to a controlled extent you
can you can basically control the color
the the outcome of the color of the uh
of the reflection hologram
so um you can do it I suppose both for
for
um for reflection and transmission but I
mean I I specifically concentrate on on
reflection Holograms because they're
just Holograms I prefer you know I
prefer the the
in both directions and the fixed colors
I mean that's what really appeals to me
with the with the reflection hologram
and it's an easier hologram to sell
compared to a white light transmission
hologram which has to be out in the
middle of a room or away from the wall
so that the light can you know go
through it
I mean that is true and I mean you know
people with transmission hold Downs
people have put mirrors behind them and
things but yeah
it rarely
um you know has the same effect of of uh
of lighting a transmission hologram how
you should which is basically from
behind you know you'd lose a certain
certain the um the brightness I suppose
um so reflection Holograms are easier
um to to eliminate than transmission
Holograms that's that's certainly true
and I suppose as a result they're easy
to sell yeah yeah now you're a scientist
by trade and uh and by learning is that
correct is that how you would describe
yourself compared to say describing
yourself as an artist or a combination
of both which is extremely important
um I would say a combination of both
actually yeah I mean I I sort of I I
initially I took the scientific Roots I
mean I became interested in Holograms
when I was about some 12 or 13. um in
probably about 1984 or 1985 and
um I I went to a an art exhibition in
London actually until my sort of the
Holograms for the first time it was a
exhibition combining photographs and
Holograms
and I I was just you know fascinated
from them you know right right from the
beginning and so actually what I then
went on to do was was um I studied
physics at Imperial College in London uh
uh you know part well mainly because of
my interest in in holography and lasers
um but uh but in recent years I've been
sort of you know doing more uh creative
and artistic it works really because
some I think I think there's there's a
huge amount of potential there with with
the pseudocolor work are you familiar
with um Steve mcgrew's hinge Point
geometry yes yeah reasonably yeah when
we're doing a pseudo-color hologram and
each of the individual exposures are
independent of one another
as far as forming or reconstructing into
three-dimensional space
the responsibility of registration with
that image is not there but with the
work that you're doing where your color
combining to create uh additive and
subtractive colors registration is
extremely important for you yeah I mean
absolutely and there are certain tricks
you know you can you have to you have
you do have to think very carefully
about the subject matter
I mean although you know if you look at
the images I've done the the things
there is quite a sort of diverse range
of different images different types of
images but you know you I I do think
very carefully to begin with about how
I'm going to you know shoot the
Holograms the the separate colors how
I'm going to separate the colors out how
easy it's going to be if we're going to
be an issue with with registration
and if there is then I have I really
have to take that thing into
consideration so for example
um one of one of the the key points to
remember is when you do a hologram of
something that's going to be multi-color
the using the feeder color process the
closer the element
plane the easier it is to register I
mean it's very difficult to have a very
deep image and have all the colors in
register uh right from the front to the
to the back of the subject matter
through the image plane so
so think about these things very
carefully
um and
you know if I'm honest you never you
never get the registration absolutely
perfect you can get it perfect on on the
surface of the Hologram but as you come
forward from the from the surface and go
back the real and virtual image you you
you actually you always have to
compromise really
um so it's it's a tricky one but it's
one of those things you've never known
until you've shot the Hollywood you've
spent weeks shooting the Hologram
whether it's whether it's actually
worked and whether you can get away with
the with the the flightless registration
if there is any yeah have you ever done
any single beam suit of color work
yeah I mean that was what I started off
with actually and
um it was I mean the the benefit
hologram is is great fun but it's it's
it was slightly limiting you couldn't
really achieve the brightness that I
wanted to achieve
um and you know some people might argue
with with that point but I I find it
difficult to to get the brightness
um that I wanted to achieve and and so
I've moved on to the the split Beam work
and and the sort of H1 H2 mastering
transfer setups where you have more
control in the sense of the uh of the
for the beam ratios and path lengths and
all the rest of it I noticed on your
website a few pictures of your
laboratory and uh you're certainly
working with some high-end professional
equipment there is it's not like you
have something stacked on type of cement
blocks
I mean that's how I started I mean I
started with the um I built a a fan
table
[Music]
um in in a shed at the bottom of my
parents Garden quite a few years ago and
uh and so anyway
that's when I was about 15 or something
and um to be honest I was you know the
the fan table is is as good in many ways
as the sort of high-end new
North Korean obstacle tables that you
can buy today I mean it's a very very
stable system that I had
um you know the downside of sand
obviously is that it it ruined Optics
very easily but um I I find it as a very
fluid type of system to use for table
geometry and lighting setups a sand
table absolutely very easy to work with
in that respect yeah and and Incredibly
stable I mean it's it's really it's a
very good um you know damping medium so
it works just as well as
um
you know the the expensive Optical
tables I mean I've I've built up a sort
of uh a certain amount of equipment over
the years really just just by you know
buying things and I could afford them
and and uh sort of buying second hand on
on the internet and things so um so now
I've got I've got I've got a lab that's
pretty pretty well equipped to be honest
with you but
um I don't think that should put anybody
off that
you can produce good Holograms
on a very limited budget when I mean
when I was when I had my sand table I
used to go down to the uh the scrap
metal merchants and get bits of Steel
and sort of weld them together and but
you know there's near amounts or Optical
posts
and they were just as good as the stuff
that you the expensive stuff that you
can buy from you know from from the
optical companies I I started off with a
small breadboard uh and it was three by
five feet
and I used that for for quite a few
years after the sand table and that was
that was brilliant because it was just
about
two people could just about lift it and
and take it from one place to another so
it was you know transportable basically
now obviously if you're working with um
the suit of color work
with reflection holography you're going
to have to work with a red laser what
type of red laser are you using are you
using a gas laser
spectrophysics
um I can't remember the model number but
it's about 25 30 milliwatts okay yeah
and so I you know I've with with that
laser I've produced Holograms up to 31
[Music]
faces yeah yeah computer color and I
mean that's the other Advantage you'll
see the color is you you know you you
only need the one laser and um I was I
was producing
um good
reflection Holograms up to eight by ten
inches with a with a five milliwatt
um he knew that I had before so you can
you read that you really don't need an
awful lot of power and you also need to
have the ability to make sure that the
Emulsion does not
shrink in the final hologram so you have
to have a processing regimen that if
you're shooting with 633 the untreated
exposure has to be 633 or it's going to
affect your other colors as well if it's
not asking too much proprietary
information what type of processing
regimen do you use
um I I use the standard processing which
which
um which many people use for reflection
Holograms and that's the paragonal based
yes developer so
um 10 grams of Park Animal uh a liter of
water and 60 grams of sodium carbonate
in a liter of water and then when you
when you make the Hologram you mix those
two part two parts together
for developing and it I mean I found it
works very very well it seems to give
the the most consistent and the
brightest results and I've experimented
with with other chemistry with other um
to the formulas and to be honest I still
get the best results with with the pi
Road based developer yeah it's what I
used to use the dichrome bleach no I
don't I don't we have a genetician
bleach oh is it see I've never used that
EDTA bleach yet but everybody seems to
be really crazy about it
is a nice simple bleach and it it
probably works um just as well but EDTA
is is is always been being there's
always been a beach that I've used
I I must admit I think it gives just
very slightly better results yeah uh a
more consistency you know with the whole
process there are there are a lot of
um
you know there's a lot of variables and
so it you know it can be frustrating
because you can start off with exactly
the right colors one day and then you
you've produced exactly you go through
the same process the next day and
something's changed the temperature or
the humidity in the in the lab and and
the the colors that you get are very
different so although I
control everything as best I can it's um
it's still it's still difficult yeah and
it can be immensely frustrating
sometimes because you you can spend a
long a long time trying to get the
colors you want achieve them and then
protest and then move on to the full
play and you end up with something
completely different voids I mean
there's also the batch of Emulsion and
things which makes a big difference yeah
the hardness
yeah I I've also noticed that the
Holograms that I've done in the past
that I have hanging here in the studio
depending on the season there's color
shift as well and this in the wintertime
I I have actually hot air heat here so
all right the atmosphere inside gets
rather dry in the winter time
and the Emulsion shrinks
and then in the location where we are it
gets very humid in the summer and the
Emulsion expands and you get your you
get your color shift for each one of the
exposures accordingly to whatever the
relative humidity of it takes a long
time for it to do it's not you know
immediate but over a week or a week and
a half you start to notice that you're
in with more humidity your Reds are
going into your deeper blood Reds and in
the winter time uh with the dry air that
the reds are actually starting to creep
a little bit towards the orange
yeah yeah absolutely and this is with
sealed Holograms too you you they're
they're seals are they yeah I mean it's
very it's very difficult to to control
really and
um you know again sometimes it can be
can be frustrating if you're if you if
you've
um you've made a hologram and the colors
are absolutely
and so the app that you spot on in in
your lab and then you take them off to
an exhibition where the temperature is
much higher and and the colors you know
to sort of go way off and it you know it
can be it can be frustrating but I think
I mean I think it purely depends on on
the temperature and temperature and the
humidity basically and how much the
Emulsion
um sort of shrinks by in in in one sixth
situation or expands in the other
situation I mean it's it's very
it's very difficult to control really
and of course the angle of the Hologram
although it's designed to be illuminated
at the angle you shoot it more or less
the you can change uh the the
Reconstruction angle um or the angle
that you illuminate the holoca math and
and that will shift the colors as well
yeah yeah I noticed with the hinge Point
geometry that I spoke about earlier it's
actually a little bit of a different
angle for each one of the color
exposures yeah absolutely Yeah a
different placement of the actual uh
diverging lens as well yeah very
interesting mathematics involved with
that yeah I mean it's they're
complicated and I must admit I
seasoning an incredible best I I really
um although I use the the you know the
technique and things but they I don't
pretend to understand it particularly
well to be honest with you
um so there is a lot of maths involved
in that and uh maths although I've got a
degree in physics it's not it's not
actually my strong point really well you
know what you're doing even though your
your background is science and your
formal training is in physics science
the actual process of what you're doing
is very very much a craft you're a
craftsperson yeah and is that important
to you to maintain that or wouldn't it
matter to you if you were to go to say a
three color laser and just started doing
full color holography is is it something
specifically that that you want to do as
a crafts person is this pseudocolor
holography
I mean there is something it actually
satisfying about about you know spending
a long time essentially crafting this
this piece spent together and ending up
over over maybe a period of weeks or
whatever with something
um as opposed to pressing a button on a
machine or I mean the true color
holography really is is also very
interesting but it just gives a
difficulty putting it into words really
but it gives a very different type of
image
it gives more like a scientific
recording of a of a of an object it's
very accurate
um but it's not necessarily particularly
appealing to look at it's like comparing
a digital DVD to seeing it with film
exactly I mean it is difficult to say
precisely what it is but um uh there's
something there it's almost too refined
um so yeah I mean I if
if I mean I suppose originally the
reason I went into the color I sort of
had it in that in that down that route
rather than true color was simply
because I didn't have the funds to
um to do true color
um but but really
what I've discovered is that is that
pseudo color
um Can can actually offer more as a
creative artistic technique than true
color in quite a few ways actually
um what ways would you say they are well
it can if you if you have an object
um the the cedar color can actually uh
enhance the features the colors
I mean I I've made quite a few Holograms
of glass for example and the diffraction
effects that you get on on glass
in the Hologram can can really
exaggerated and so they they they
transform this sort of Fairly ordinary
looking piece of glass into something
quite special
um and and you don't I mean I have
experimented with true color and you
just don't get the same kind of effect
maybe it's simply because of the
diffraction efficiency the brightness of
the Holograms
um but uh but I have a feeling there's a
few other things there as well really
um so yeah it's a combination of
different things really and
um I I think I think the theater color
has the potential
um you know to be to be
more creative in a sense
one of the pseudocolor works that I did
was a three color piece and I took
Plexiglas and put it into the oven until
it got soft
and when when it came out of the oven
I bent the plexiglass and twisted it in
different dimensions while it was still
soft
then spray painted the Plexiglas black
and while the spray paint was still wet
I would take paint brushes and make
different areas where it would make the
Plexiglas clear
also take cotton swabs on some of them
and I would dabble the cotton swabs on
the different pieces of Plexiglas
and then what I would do is rear
illuminate them sort of like a shadow
gram in a sense the shadowgram geometry
rear illuminate them and the areas that
I use the paint brushes on and the
cotton swabs would allow the laser light
to come through
and each one of the pieces of Plexiglas
I did a separate color
first three color suit to color hologram
and a lot of the different areas
actually occupied the same
three-dimensional space and one of the
paintbrush swabs would actually go
through an area of the cotton swabs
and I noticed on your web page a lot of
the whole the Holograms are absolutely
gorgeous and you seem to be almost
documenting already existing objects and
I was just curious do you have any plans
for now or in the future of actually
using something else other than already
existing objects
in your work yeah I mean I've I've done
uh you know I haven't done an awful lot
of abstracts um Holograms but I've but
I've done a few
um and I mean I've there's one
there's one which I was particularly
pleased with called color wave uh I
think that's on the website I'm pretty
sure it is actually and and that
actually that was I mean plexigas is
like perspex isn't it really is that
what you call essentially perspex isn't
it yeah it's it's a frosted type of
plastic a lot of people will use them in
like shower doors so that they don't
have real glass and things like
a similar technique that for creating
that that the sculpture basically the
the color wave and um so that that was
basically one of the the sort of first
abstract more abstract pieces that I did
I suppose the the the the earlier stuff
like um uh the the the one of Gromit for
example I mean that was that was just
simply a model that I saw and for me
that was a technical challenge to try
and
um that was one of the very earliest
pieces I did back in 1997. so I I just
from a technical point of view wanted to
recreate that and the Hologram and make
it as as bright as possible and
um as technically uh perfect as possible
and um so I pick
pick something like that with
from a technical point of view very
challenging from a creative point of
view apart from the creative process of
making the Hologram
um not so challenging but but now I'm
moving more into the sort of abstract
type images yeah and um I've I've I find
that very interesting I'll make sure
that there's a link to your website on
the holotalk page so people will be able
to listen to the show and go over and
visit your site and you also have
holograms for sale over there as well
they'll have to do the conversion I
guess from what is it called their
British Sterling or British pounds or
something and uh yeah so what is it just
pretty much for a U.S funds double that
amount I would imagine or so is that
correct it's roughly roughly double so
yeah 100 would be 50
um pound sterling yeah roughly yeah
since we're coming up on almost a half
an hour already I was wondering if
there's uh anything that you'd like to
add to the interview that we didn't talk
about
um
I I can't think of them I mean is there
anything that you you'd like me to add
let's put it that way oh well um I mean
I could I could carry on talking for
hours oh I bet you Chris I'd love to
talk for hours
I have to keep the file sizes small
because of all the people that download
the files yeah absolutely some of them
overseas don't have high speed
connections and believe it or not
there's still adult people that are
going on the internet with 14 4 modems
are you so it would take quite a bit of
time for you to download one of these
shows on one of those modems
that's why I try and keep it uh I'd love
to talk to people for an hour or more
and I know there's plenty of things to
talk about but absolutely yeah so do you
do you exhibit your you have any
exhibits of your Holograms coming up
that you'd like to promote or is there
anything that you'd like to promote do
you have workshops
um I I don't at the moment actually and
exhibitions I mean the last exhibition I
did actually was that the um uh the the
conference in in Wales
um where they had an exhibition of one
of the castles down there is there
anyone that you have that was an
influence
for you
um
I'll be honest that there wasn't really
because because there's been so little
see the color work really done um were
you familiar with John Kaufman the name
John Kaufman
seen some of his stuff quite quite
recently actually
um and in fact there was an exhibition
of his his work over here about about
some six months or a year ago
um Melissa Crenshaw the is another name
that did some beautiful suit I met her
in in um in Wales yeah and the thing is
it's very difficult I find it uh I still
find it quite difficult to find sort of
some information about these people and
and photographs because I mean one of
the one of the at the um the conference
I actually gave a talk
found sort of you know the history of
theater color work and and um and I
missed out a few people not not
intentionally but simply because I I
didn't know that they they produced that
for these kinds of holograms and it's
just been it's just quite difficult to
find um information on it to be honest
with you yeah it is very difficult to
find information I think I think Klein
Moore is another name I I hope I'm not
oh yeah
I hope I'm not forgetting people and if
I do I apologize but to get back to what
you were originally talking about when I
in politely interrupted you you you have
exhibits coming up
um I don't actually at the moment no no
um nothing nothing uh
um in the imminent future but I I hope
to be organizing
um something perhapsulated in the uh how
do you feel about that there you know to
me with the type of work that you do and
the quality of that work
you should be turning shows down because
there's too many of them trying to get
you work how do you feel about I mean
that that's just Insanity to me that's
absolute Insanity I mean it is in a way
um a um it's it's it's partly my fault I
think because I don't push it enough and
and you know I've I've sort of involved
in so many other things as well and it's
really a question of finding the time
because uh you know setting up an extra
properly is is is something that takes a
lot of time and effort and quite a large
quite a large amount of money as well
sometimes so
um but but so I I am certainly partly to
blame for for not uh for not pushing my
stuff enough I mean I've literally only
within the past six months um organized
my my website and that's something I've
been meaning to do for years yeah
um but yeah I mean there are very few
places that that some sort of exhibit
holograms on a regular basis is I mean
it's as simple as that and and
in the UK we used to have you know three
or four
galleries that were dedicated to
exhibiting Holograms and and various
other galleries such as the photography
gatherers that would be
um putting on regular exhibitions and
Holograms now now there's no one I mean
well there's Jonathan Ross who has his
Gallery in London yes but um but
very very few people very very few
venues where you can you can exhibit
your hologram so it is difficult it's
very difficult and of course it's very
difficult to for people to get an idea
of what they're like really on the on on
the internet looking at looking at
photographs absolutely
it's heartbreaking
it is in a way but I hope I hope that um
I hope the interest will come back
well folks like yourself with the work
that you're doing I'm sure that help you
know having people see
people see quality and
and the care and the craftsmanship that
goes into craftspersonship that goes
into
the work that you do yeah well I mean
you know the the more people that try it
the better really and I think that some
I think what what you're doing and the
you know for example The holography
Forum I mean that's just it's a
statistic idea and it's it's great to
see that there are people out there that
are
um that are experimenting with this and
and trying uh and making Holograms
because sometimes you wonder if there's
anyone else out there that's making a
lot of sense yeah
but sometimes it's a good thing to turn
a computer off and get involved in your
own community at the local community
level as well so I'd like to say that to
people you know because I know I know
sometimes we're we think what a
wonderful Global Community we have on
the internet and a lot of times the time
that we take you know with this Global
electronic uh phosphorus screen
Communications uh we let other I
wouldn't say more important things but
just important as far there's our local
communities our local Arts organizations
and things of that nature we just don't
bother with because we have such a
wonderful Community online but online's
not going to do it you know it's it's
the people on the street spending more
time talking to people uh the other side
of the world than we do next door that's
true
well I want to thank you very much for
taking the time to come on the show I
know it's going to be a great show and I
think it's a problem yeah this will
probably go up in February sometime I
would imagine I've got the Apollo
astronaut up there right now then
there's a large holography exhibit
that's coming not too far from where I
live in one of the museums here that's
have been curated by Paul Barefoot who
name of Photography traveling exhibit of
Through the Looking Glass together so I
have to I act that opens on February 3rd
so the next show has to be the one that
I did earlier today with the marketing
director of the museum and then you'll
go up after that how's that fantastic
but at least we have it finished
I hope to get a chance to meet you
sometime if you're ever in the states
I'm only about a little bit over an hour
maybe depending on traffic an hour and a
half away from New York City
and only an hour away from new from
Philadelphia so if you're ever in the
states and you're in those areas please
let me know I'd love to meet you that
would be fantastic yeah and if I mean if
you can't come to me I'll come to you
but if you can come here you know come
we'll have a nice dinner and everything
you know that'll be brilliant and I mean
I've been I've been really interested
because I've had a lot of I've had your
name mentioned you know many times and
um but never know never known quite
where you sort of fit in the picture
have you've been involved in filmography
for many years is that right
since I was popping pimples
it's uh it's holography so
Fitness
so I'm glad I'm not the only one all
right take care yeah Andy speaking
bye-bye